# TIMOTHY DAVIS CALHOUN Full Stack Software Developer

Strategic thinker with 8 years of work experience solving problems, creating custom tools, and optimizing processes - transitioning into a software development career. Diverse skillset – broad programming knowledge, engineering degree, and extensive data science experience. Calculated communicator adept at presenting solutions and generating real, quantifiable results. Eager to provide value and make an impact at your company as a software developer. Will relocate.

## **Technical Skills**

- Programming/Development
  - Languages C#, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, XML, JSON
  - o Frameworks/Libraries ASP.NET MVC, Django, Bootstrap, jQuery, React
  - Database Technologies Microsoft SQL Server, SQLite
  - o Version Control GitHub & GitHub Desktop Application, Git Bash, Team Foundation Server
  - o **IDE's** Visual Studio, PyCharm, IDLE
- Engineering Degree in civil engineering with an aptitude for solving complex technical problems.
- **Data Science** Proficient in all segments of the data science life cycle capture, maintenance, process, analysis and the ability to communicate the data with visualizations & reports that improve business intelligence and aid in decision making.
- Process Analysis Able to identify procedural gaps, redundancies, and inefficiencies and construct optimized solutions.
- **Technical Writing** Experience with procedural technical documentation.
- Microsoft Office Suite Excel, Word, PowerPoint, Access

### **Professional and Personal Skills**

- Self-motivated solution architect identified multiple inefficient processes and created new tools and solutions, reducing
  daily data entry by over 50% and improving decision making. This was not in my job description I simply recognized an
  opportunity.
- Superb communicator, capable of taking ownership of a tool or process and educating team members. Sole trainer for cost estimation software to over 50 colleagues.
- Flexible and adaptable team member that can take on leadership or supporting roles. Regularly hosted data technologist coding review meetings while performing QA/QC of data.
- Excellent technical writer. Able to communicate objectives clearly and concisely. Secondary author of Chevron's Gulf of Mexico Well Cost Estimation and Forecasting Guidance Document.
- Expert level score on Indeed.com assessments: Problem Solving, Critical Thinking, and Data Analysis

### **Professional Experience**

# Internship – Full Stack Software Development (Jul 2019 – Aug 2019) Prosper IT Consulting – Golden, CO

- Four consecutive 2-week sprints developing a real-world application in an agile/scrum environment.
- Within the ASP.NET MVC design framework, I expanded my knowledge of C#, HTML, CSS, and JS/jQuery by implementing a dynamic password validation box, mobile compatibility enhancements, dynamic navbar with translating icon, and styled & animated footer. Additionally, I debugged a problem with a geolocation API.
- Within the Django framework, I developed my skills working with Python, HTML, and JavaScript by designing a graph that would take user inputs from a data entry form, pass them through the view, and display them.
- Sample code can be found via my portfolio or GitHub.

## Data Technologist – Deepwater Exploration and Projects (Jan 2013 – Dec 2018) Chevron - Houston, TX

- Improved organizational efficiency and enabled rapid data analysis by developing custom cost forecasting and well
  monitoring tool for engineers and management (Self-taught VBA to accomplish). Used regularly to aid in high-impact
  decisions. Daily data entry by users reduced by over 50%.
- Pivotal member of a team overhauling well estimation process reduced end of well forecast variance from >10% to <3%.</li>
- Enhanced interpersonal and leadership skills as the host of a monthly training course for time and cost estimation software.
- Developed technical writing skills by constructing technical guidance documents for various procedures to be used by the business unit.
- Designed, improved, and maintained offset data to be used in well cost estimation. Includes development of data structure and optimization for usability. Utilized for the construction of 9-figure, deepwater well estimates

# Civil Engineering EIT – Public Works (Sep 2010 – May 2012) Brown and Gay Engineers - Houston, TX

- Improved problem-solving skills by performing water system database analysis in Excel, including developing complex formulae, cost analysis, goal seeking, and process optimization.
- General QA/QC of water line plans, specifications, contract documentation, and various engineering reports to ensure compliance with regulations and verify accuracy and consistency.
- Developed managerial skills through aiding in design-bid process. Scheduled and coordinated all stages from advertisement, pre-bid to bid opening to ensure seamless and efficient process execution.

## **Education and Training**

## **Software Development**

The Tech Academy - Denver CO (Mar 2019 - Aug 2019)

Six-month Software Development Boot Camp with hands on work covering a variety of topics: fundamentals of technology & computer science, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Python, C#, SQL & database design/management, and Version Control. Includes four 2-week sprints for a consulting company, working in Azure DevOps. These projects allow students to test and expand their knowledge by writing original code to solve problems while working with a team.

Bachelor of Science, Civil Engineering – GPA 3.67 University of Texas at Austin (Aug 2005 – May 2009)

Additional employment experience as well as references and test scores are available upon request